Luiz Heitor Corrêa de Azevedo collection on Latin American Folklore
Library of Congress American Folklife Center Archive of Folk Culture
- Castro, Zaíde Maciel de e Aracy do Prado Couto. Folias de Reis. São Paulo: Prefeitura do Município de São Paulo Secretaria de Educação e Cultura Divisão do Arquivo Histórico, 1959. (Box-item 2/49)
  This overview of Folia de Reis was collected in two different areas of Rio de Janeiro, Caxias and Nova Iguaçu. The publication connects the past cultural exchange of these areas with the Distrito Federal region in Brazil, and describes the people involved in the Folia de Reis, the tradition itself, and some literature that inspired this performance.
- Castro, Zaíde Maciel de e Aracy do Prado Couto. "Folias de Reis." Cadernos de Folclore 16 (no date): 3-22. (Box-item 2/50)
  This study focuses on twelve different Folia de Reis groups in Rio de Janeiro, who celebrate Christmas and the Epiphany between December 24 and January 6.
- Castro, Zaíde Maciel de e Aracy do Prado Couto. "Folias de Reis." Cadernos de Folclore 16 (1961): 7-82. (Box-item 2/51)
  A study of the tradition of Folia de Reis in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, and the population's enactment of the trip made by the Three Kings to visit the infant Jesus in Bethlehem.
- Centro de Pesquisas Folclóricas. A Escola Nacional de Música e as pesquisas de folklore musical no Brasil. Rio de Janeiro: Universidade do Brasil, 1943. (Box-item 3/52)
  A description of the plans of the School of Music in Rio de Janeiro to investigate Brazilian popular music.
- Chiarini, João. Cururu. São Paulo: Departamento de Cultura, 1947. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 3/53)
  Cururu is the name given to the dispute, or poetry combat between the people, curueiros, engaged in this repetitive oral tradition. This publication offers the background of Cururu, discusses the vocabulary used in these disputes, presents pictures, and provides short biographies of some curueiros.
- Círculo Folclórico Luso Brasileiro do Liceu Literário Português. Rio de Janeiro: Liceu Literário Português, 1951. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 3/54)
  This booklet celebrates the foundation of the association formed by Portuguese and Brazilian folklorists. It describes the purpose of the group, the plan to create a museum of folklore, as well as examples of folk tales and legends of both countries.
- Colóquio Internacional de Estudos Luso-Brasileiros. Uma festa de Xangô no Opô Afonjá. Bahia: Universidade da Bahia, 1959. (Box-item 3/55)
  A publication that was distributed to the participants of the Fourth International Convention of Portuguese and Brazilian Studies. It includes a brief description of the African-based religious practices in Bahia, Brazil.
- Comissão Nacional de Folclore. II Semana Nacional de Folclore, 16 a 22 de agosto de 1949, São Paulo. Meeting: Semana Nacional de Folclóre, 2d, São Paulo, Brazil, 1949. (Box-item 3/56)
  A program of events from the "Second National Week" celebrating Brazilian folklore. Besides the list of activities, the program provides a brief summary of marujada and moçambique, two traditional dances of Portuguese and African origin, respectively.
- Congresso Brasileiro de Folclore. Anais [do] 1o Congresso brasileiro de folclore, Rio de Janeiro, de 22 a 31 de Agôsto de 1951. Rio de Janeiro: Ministério das Relações Exteriores, Serviço de publicações, 1953. (Box-item 3/57)
  A program of the events, lectures, and participants of the First Brazilian Congress of Folklore.
- Conservatório Brasileiro de Música. A Influência do Folclóre na Música Erudita. Rio de Janeiro, 1951. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 3/58)
  A study of the influence of folklore on the classical music of Brazil.
- Conservatório Dramático e Musical de São Paulo. Folclore Nacional: Referências sôbre fatos folclóricos de interêsse musical apresentadas em trabalhos realizados durante o ano de 1946. São Paulo, 1947. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 3/59)
  A collection of traditional music and dances from different areas of Brazil.
- Conservatório Dramático e Musical de S. Paulo. Folclore Nacional: Resultado de um inquérito sôbre mitos do Estado de São Paulo, realizado em setembro e outubro de 1947 – Duas congadas de S. Paulo e uma de Minas Gerais – "(Festa do Santo Rei," de Minas Gerais). São Paulo, 1948. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 3/60)
  A collection of legends, myths, and traditional dance festivities from the states of São Paulo and Minas Gerais in Brazil.
- Correa, Roberto Nunes. Viola Caipira. Brasília: MusiMed, 1983. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 3/61)
  According to the author, the main objective of this publication is to register as much information as possible about the viola caipira, a bowed stringed instrument that is slightly larger than a violin. The book has information about the origin of the viola, its characteristics, and some sheet music.
- Corrêa, Waldemar (Dino Desidério). A Volta de Antônio Chimango. Comissão Nacional de Folclore do I.B.E.C.C. Instituto Brasileiro de Educação, Ciência e Cultura – Comissão Brasileira da Organização Educacional, Científíca e Cultural das Nações Unidas (UNESCO) no. 21 (1958): 13-28. (Box-item 3/62)
  A political parody of an earlier publication titled Antonio Chimango by Ramiro Barcelos. This parody is considered part of the "traditional gaúcho movement" from Rio Grande do Sul and it was published during the 100th anniversary of the Farroupilha War in Brazil.
- Côrtes, J.C. Paixão e Luís Carlos Barbosa Lessa. Manual de danças gaúchas. Pôrto Alegre, 1956. (Box-item 3/63)
  A collection of extensive research conducted in 62 counties of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil. The study is limited to the most typical and characteristic dances found in these areas.
- Echenique, Sylvio da Cunha. Bruaca: Coletanea de provérbios regionalistas 17. Comissão Gaúcha de Folclore, 1958. (Box-item 3/64)
  A collection of regional proverbs from the state of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil.
- Eduardo, Otávio da Costa. Aspectos do folclore de uma comunidade rural. São Paulo: Departamento de Cultura, 1951. (Box-item 3/65)
  Eduardo collected short stories with African roots from people living in the rural areas of Brazil. His book analyzes the tribal origins of these short stories, the reason they were preserved, and the modifications that happened after they arrived in Brazil. He compares this material with Afro-Brazilian folklore in other areas of the country.
- Escola Nacional de Música, Classe de Folclore Nacional, Textos musicais para exemplificação: Melodias de Indios do Brasil (extraidas da "Rondônia" de Roquette-Pinto), I-II. Prepared for Escola Nacional de Música. (Box-item 3/66)
  A collection of musical scores of Brazilian songs that were used in a folk music class at the National Music School in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.
- Escola Nacional de Música, Classe de Folclore Nacional, Exemplos musicais: Fados Portugueses, II. Prepared for Escola Nacional de Música. (Box-item 3/67)
  A collection of musical scores of Portuguese fados, such as Canção Joanina, Fado da Madrugada, and Fado Visconti, used in a folklore music class at the National Music School in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.
- Escola Nacional de Música, Classe de Folclore Nacional, Textos musicais para exemplificação: Melodias Africanas, III. Prepared for Escola Nacional de Música (Box-item 3/68)
  Scores for a group of African melodies such as Canto de remadores (Costa dos Escravos), used in a folklore music class at the National Music School in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.
- Escola Nacional de Música, Classe de Folclore Nacional, Textos musicais para exemplificação: Melodias recolhidas por Mário de Andrade (Ensaio sobre a Música Brasileira), IV. Prepared for Escola Nacional de Música. (Box-item 3/69)
  Musical scores of selections of regional melodies from various parts of Brazil collected by Mário de Andrade.
- Ferreira, Ascenço. "O Maracatú." Arquivos 2 (1942): 1-22. (Box-item 3/70)
  This publication describes the tradition of Maracatú in Brazil.
- Ferretti, Sérgio, Valdelino Cécio, Joila Moraes, e Roldão Lima. "Tambor de Crioula." Cadernos de Folclore 31 (1981): 3-59. (Box-item 3/71)
  A study of the tradition of Tambor de Crioula in the state of Maranhão, Brazil, which is characterized by a dance with African roots that praises Saint Benedito, known as the "black saint."
- Fondo Nacional de las Artes. (Argentina). Dia Mundial del Folklore, 1965. (Box-item 3/72)
  A program listing the main events of the Second Folklore World Day held in Corrientes, Argentina.
- Freitas, Luiz G. Gomes de. "Antigos Jogos Desportivos da Campanha." Comissão Nacional de Folclore do I.B.E.C.C. Instituto Brasileiro de Educação, Ciência e Cultura – Comissão Brasileira da Organização Educacional, Científíca e Cultural das Nações Unidas (UNESCO) no. 10 (1957): 12-19. (Box-item 3/73)
  This essay discusses the various traditional games played in the state of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil.
- Freitas, Luiz G. Gomes de. "Estâncias Antigas Veículos de Carga Cânhamo e Linho." Comissão Nacional de Folclore do I.B.E.C.C. Instituto Brasileiro de Educação, Ciência e Cultura – Comissão Brasileira da Organização Educacional, Científíca e Cultural das Nações Unidas (UNESCO) no. 3 (1954): 41-85. [Inscribed on cover.] (Box-item 3/74)
  A study of the folkloric significance of the old farming estates in the state of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil. The author focuses on the different means of transport and the history of the linen industry.
- Geisel, Amália Lucy; Raul Giovanni da Motta; Maia Isa; Fundação Nacional de Arte (Brazil). Artesanato brasileiro. Rendas. Rio de Janeiro: Edição FUNARTE, 1981. (Box-item 3/75)
  A photographic study of the materials and techniques used by textile artisans.
- Gonçalves, Martin. "Théâtre et Danses populaires du Brésil." La Danse: Revue Mensuelle Internationale 29 (1957): 19-26. (Box-item 3/76)
  Description of the work of the Théâtre et Danses populaires du Brésil in preserving and documenting traditional Brazilian dances, with photographs of performances.
- Halmos, I. Melody and form in the music of the Nambicuara Indians (Mato Grosso, Brazil). Budapest, 1964. (Box-item 4/77)
  A study of the Nambicuara Indians by I. Halmos, which is based on the collection of Lajos Boglár, a Brazilian anthropologist, who visited the Nambicuara Indians in 1959.
- Harcourt, Marguerite Béclard d'; Harcourt, Raoul d'. La musique des Aymara sur les hauts plateaux boliviens. Paris: Musée de L'homme, 1959. (Box-item 4/78)
  On the music, instruments, dances, and musicians of the Aymara Indians from the high plains of Bolivia.
- Herrera, Ataliva. Folklore y nativismo en la enseñanza primaria: Resolución del Consejo Nacional de Educación creando la Comision de Folklore y Nativismo. República Argentina: Consejo Nacional de Educación, 1945. (Box-item 4/79)
  In this essay, Herrera emphasizes the importance of expanding the population's knowledge about folklore in Argentina, especially during the early school grades.
- Hessel, Lothar. Antenor Moraes: Escritor regionalista do Rio Grande do Sul. Comissão Gaúcha de Folclore, 1958. (Box-item 4/80)
  A brief introduction of the writer Antenor Moraes, poet and social leader from Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil, with a short memoir written by Moraes himself.
- Hornbostel, Erich Moritz von. La musica de los Makuschí, Taulipáng y Yekuana. Venezuela: Universidad Central de Venezuela, Facultad de Humanidades y Educación, no date. [Inscribed on the cover.] (Box-item 4/81)
  A short study about the music and musical instruments from northern Brazil and Venezuela that were influenced by these three indigenous groups living in the region of the River Ventuari.
- Instituto Brasileiro de Educação Ciência e Cultura. Correio do IBECC: Boletim Trimestral do Instituto Brasileiro de Educação, Ciência e Cultura. 21 (1963): 1-31. (Box-item 4/82)
  This publication summarizes the events of the fifth Brazilian Folklore Congress held in Fortaleza, Ceará in 1963.
- Instituto Brasileiro de Educação Ciência e Cultura. Exposição de arte popular da semana folclórica, 1948. (Box-item 4/83)
  This pamphlet was distributed during the celebration of the Folkloric week in Rio de Janeiro in 1948. The publication contains an introduction emphasizing the importance of preserving the country's traditions, illustrations of folkloric expressions, and includes a brief article discussing the word "folklore."
- Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatística, Departamento Estadual de Estatística. O Boi de Mamão no Folclore Catarinense. Série C (1949): 1-30. (Box-item 4/84)
  Boi de Mamão is a folkloric tradition in Brazil characterized by the visit and dance of a wood framed ox covered with fabric. Boi de Mamão is the name given in the state of Santa Catarina to the northeast tradition of bumba-meu-boi, also knowm in Paraná as boi-bumbá.
- Instituto de Folklore (Venezuela). "Danza de la Candelaria." Revista Educación 87 (Abril de 1958): 5-23. (Box-item 4/85)
  Description of all aspects of this Venezuelan dance: the body movements, the music, the characters, and the ten movements in which the dance is divided.
- Instituto de Folklore (Venezuela). "El Carite." Revista Educación 81 (Febrero de 1956): 3-20. (Box-item 4/86)
  El Carite describes the ritual performance of fishing in Venezuela, including the lyrics, dances, and drawings of the costumes associated with this performance.
- Instituto de Folklore (Venezuela). "El Mampulorio." Revista Educación 84 (Diciembre de 1956): 3-14. (Box-item 4/87)
  El Mampulorio describes a game with music and dance that was performed by the general population in Venezuela after the death of a child. As a result of its endearing music and dance, the "El Mampulorio" tradition was transferred to schools. The book describes the lyrics, choreography, and characters involved in this practice.
- Instituto de Folklore (Venezuela). "El Maremare." Revista Educación 85 (Junio de 1957): 3-18. (Box-item 4/88)
  Describes the choreography, music, and clothing related to the performance of el maremare in Venezuela. This practice originated from indigenous groups in Venezuela and was adopted by the general population.
- Instituto de Folklore (Venezuela). "El Pájaro Guarandol." Revista Educación 77 (Junio de 1955): 3-24. (Box-item 4/89)
  Describes the elements involved in this traditional Venezuelan dance.
- Instituto de Folklore (Venezuela). "La Burriquita." Revista Educación 19 (Octubre de 1955): 5-23. (Box-item 4/90)
  Describes the songs, body movements, and costumes used during this form of performance in Venezuela. La Burriquita has its origins in Europe, and it is performed mostly in carnivals and during Christmas.
- Instituto de Folklore (Venezuela). "Los Chimichimitos." Revista Educación 82 (Abril de 1956): 5-19. (Box-item 4/91)
  Describes the music, dance, and characters involved in this popular children's tradition of Venezuela.
- Instituto de Folklore (Venezuela). "Semejanza de los Pastores." Revista Educación 91 (Noviembre de 1960): 3-34. (Box-item 4/92)
  Describes Semejanza de los Pastores or Pastores de San Joaquín, a representation that happens in some areas in the state of Carabobo, Venezuela, to honor the birth of Jesus on the night of December 24.
- Instituto Interamericano de Etnomusicología y Folklore. Biblioteca INIDEF. Caracas, Venezuela. 1-8. (Box-item 4/93)
  This publication introduces the Inter-American Institute of Ethnomusicology and Folklore in Venezuela. It describes the archives of the institution as well as its educational activities and publications.
- Instituto Mexicano de Musicologia y Folklore. Boletín Instituto Mexicano de Musicologia y Folklore 1 (1940): 1-72. (Box-item 4/94)
  The Mexican Institute of Musicology and Folklore presents articles about Mexican traditions such as music, a calendar listing the national celebrations, and literature.
- Junqueira, Oswaldo Gomes. "A Farinhada." Comissão Nacional de Folclore do I.B.E.C.C. Instituto Brasileiro de Educação, Ciência e Cultura – Comissão Brasileira da Organização Educacional, Científica e Cultural das Nações Unidas (UNESCO) no. 5 (1954): 271-273. [Inscribed on cover.] (Box-item 4/95)
  A brief description of Farinhada, the production of manioc flour, which takes place in the state of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil.
- Lamas, Dulce Martins. A Influência Portuguesa na Música Popular Brasileira. Rio de Janeiro: Tese com que se apresenta Dulce Martins Lamas ao concurso de livre docência da cadeira de Folclore Musical, 1949. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 4/96)
  Lamas examines the Portuguese influence on the popular music in Brazil with a focus on music from the rural regions of Brazil.
- Lamas, Dulce Martins. Contribuição de Portugal ao folclore musical brasileiro. Rio de Janeiro: Jornal do Commercio – Rodrigues & Cia, 1954. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 4/97)
  Lamas writes about the Portuguese influence on the rhymes and lyrics found in Brazilian folklore.
- Lane, Frederico. Armas e Técnicas de Briga nas Regiões Rurais de Sâo Paulo: (1. Prêmio no 6. Concurso de Mongrafias sôbre o Folclore Nacional, instituído em 1951 pela Discoteca Pública Municipal, do Departamento de Cultura, da Prefeitura do Município de São Paulo). São Paulo: Departamento de Cultura, 1958. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 4/98)
  This monograph discusses the different weapons and techniques, including guns and knives, used by the rural population to protect themselves in fights.
- Laytano, Dante de. "Lendas do Rio Grande do Sul" Comissão Nacional de Folclore do I.B.E.C.C. Instituto Brasileiro de Educação, Ciência e Cultura das Nações Unidas (UNESCO) no. 9 (1956) (Box-item 4/99)
  Legends from Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil.
- Laytano, Dante de. O Folclore do Rio Grande do Sul. Pôrto Alegre, 1952. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 4/100)
  A short overview of folklore in the state of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil.
- Laytano, Dante de. O Folclore do Rio Grande do Sul: Tradições Populares do Cíclo Agropastoril. Pôrto Alegre, no date. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 4/101)
  Focuses on the tradition of Pixuru that is practiced in the state of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil, and entails the owner of a farm offering food to twenty of his friends and neighbors who in return spend the day planting crops in his farm.
- Laytano, Dante de. O Negro no Rio Grande do Sul: Separata de "Primeiro Seminário de Estudos Gaúchos ." Pôrto Alegre: Comissão Nacional de Folclore, 1958. (Box-item 4/102)
  An in-depth study about the meaning of the Portuguese word negro used in Brazil to indicate the portion of the population with African roots. It also discusses whether this population existed in Rio Grande do Sul in the beginning of the exploration of the state.
- León, Argeliers. "Elebwa: Una Divinidad de la Santería Cubana." Abhandlungen und Berichte des Staatlichen Museums für Völkerkunde Dresden 21 (1962): 57-60. (Box-item 4/103)
  A discussion of the role of the divine spirit, Elebwa, in the practice of santería. It also explains that santería is a pejorative term used to refer to the Afro-Cuban syncretic belief system that combines the beliefs of the West African Yoruba people with elements of worship from Roman Catholicism.
- León, Argeliers. El paso de elementos por nuestro folklore. La Habana, 1952. (Box-item 4/104)
  Elements of folklore that influenced the music in Cuba
- León, Argeliers. El patrimonio folklórico musical cubano. La Habana, 1952. (Box-item 4/105)
  El patrimonio folklórico musical cubano complements the publication El paso de elementos por nuestro folklore. According to the author of these materials, the book examines the roots and characteristics of musical expression in Cuban folklore.
- León, Maria Teresa Linares de. Ensayo sobre la influencia española en la musica cubana: Premio "Maria Teresa Garcia Montes de Giberga 1958 ." La Habana, 1958. (Box-item 4/106)
  This brief essay discusses the Spanish influence on Cuban music.
- León, Maria Teresa Linares de. Ensayo sobre la influencia africana en la musica de Cuba: Premio "Maria Teresa Garcia Montes de Giberga 1959 ." La Habana, 1959. (Box-item 4/107)
  An essay on African influences on Cuban music since the colonization of the country.
- Lessa, Barbosa. Índice do arquivo de danças brasileiras de Barbosa Lessa: 518 minutos de gravação em rotação 4.75 cm/seg. São Paulo: Francisco Alves, 1959. (Box-item 4/108)
  Index to sound recordings of Brazilian dance and music recorded by Barbosa Lessa.
- Lima, Rossini Tavares de. Achegas ao estudo do romanceiro no Brasil. São Paulo: Prefeitura do Município de São Paulo, Secretaria de Educação e Cultura, Divisão do Arquivo Histórico, 1959. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 4/109)
  Analysis of ancient Iberian romances and Brazilian oral traditions collected by the author.
- Lima, Rossini Tavares de. A malhação de Judas em São Paulo. São Paulo, Prefeitura do Município de São Paulo, Secretaria de Educação, 1959. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 4/110)
  A description of the tradition of beating and burning an effigy of Judas Iscariot. The practice of malhação de Judas occurs on the Holy Saturday of Holy Week, prior to Easter Sunday, and today it occurs mostly in the inner cities of Brazil.
- Lima, Rossini Tavares de. Folguedos populares do Brasil: Maracatu, congada, moçambique, reisado, guerreiro, folia de reis, dança dos tapuios, cabocolinhos, caiapó, bumba-meu-boi e outros folguedos dos boi, chegança e fandango ou Marujada. São Paulo: Ricordi, 1962. (Box-item 4/111)
  Documents a vast number of popular and traditional dances and celebrations from different areas of Brazil.
- Machado, Propício da Silveira. Pereira Coruja: Vida e obra 16. Pôrto Alegre: Comissão Nacional Folclore do Instituto Brasileiro de Educação, Ciência e Cultura: Comissão Brasileira da Organização Educacional, Cientifica e Cultural das Nações Unidas, Unesco, 1958. (Box-item 4/112)
  Conference proceedings honoring the life and work of Antônio Álvares Pereira Coruja, a politician, educator, and the author of the first regional vocabulary of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil.
- Magalhães, Basílio de, João da Silva Campos. O folclore no Brasil: Com uma coletânea de 81 contos populares. Rio de Janeiro: Imprensa Nacional, 1939. (Box-item 5/113)
  A collection of 81 popular short stories from the state of Bahia, with other aspects of the Brazilian folklore, such as the Native Indian and African contributions to the traditions of the country.
- Martínez Furé, Rogelio. Conjunto folklórico nacional. La Habana: Consejo Nacional de Cultura, 1963. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 5/114)
  A study of the musical and traditional manifestations of Cuban folklore. With a vast number of pictures, the book also includes short biographies of the people who were interviewed during the study.
- Martins, Saul. Artes e ofícios caseiros. São Paulo: Prefeitura, 1959. (Box-item 5/115)
  This publication presents the diverse artwork created by the general Brazilian population inside their homes. Some of the examples are pottery, baked goods, baskets, and sewing. There is a vocabulary list in the book related to these traditions as well.
- Mélo, Veríssmo de. Acalantos. Edição da Revista, no date. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 5/116)
  The word acalanto refers to the act of cuddling and singing for a child while he/she falls asleep. This publication is a short compilation of these traditional songs and lullabies from Brazil.
- Mélo, Veríssmo de. Superstições de São João. Natal: Bando, 1949. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 5/117)
  One of a series of short studies on the folklore of the state of Rio Grande do Norte. This publication details the popular beliefs that are involved in the traditional celebration of São João, Saint John.
- Mello, Moraes. Artistas do meu tempo: Seguidos de um estudo sobre Laurindo Rabello. Rio de Janeiro: H. Garnier, [Inscribed.] 1904. (Box-item 5/118)
  Features some of the distinguished artists of 1904. The publication also gives detailed information about Laurindo Rabello, a writer and poet from Rio de Janeiro.